你在这儿啊
There you are.
嗨, 我只是想偷闲呼吸一下新鲜空气
Hey, I was just stealing a breath of fresh air.
我原以为你在探测这个城市
I thought you were off exploring the city.
正准备去
About to.
我在大陆找到了这个athosians人做的
I picked this up on the mainland.
The athosians made it.
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
很漂亮
It's beautiful.
你是怎么知道我的生日的?
How did you find out?
这我可不会说
Mum's the word.
行了, 我们已经检查完生活区了
继续前进
All right, we're done with the living quarters.
We're moving on.
等, 等, 等一下, 在你走之前
告诉我你有没有发现比我们现在更好的住处?
Whoa, whoa, whoa, before you go,
did you see any better than our current quarters?
有一些
A few.
实际上, 其中有几个相当不错
Some of them are pretty nice, actually.
那好, 他们的面积大概有多大?
Well, what kind of square footage
are we talking about?
我是谁, 你的房产经纪人么, Rodney?
What am I, your realtor, Rodney?
我们来这里是要解开Atlantis的秘密
We're here to unlock the secrets of Atlantis.
没错, 是这样, 我正在找一个带书房的单人卧室
最好还带个阳台, 不过这个我不强求
Yeah, well, I'm looking for a one-bedroom with a den.
Preferably with a balcony, but I'm not married to it.
长官, 来看这个
Sir, check this out.
我们最好还是让自己舒服一点
至少在幽灵来这以前...
We might as well be comfortable,
at least until the Wraith get here...
别说了, 等一下
shut up for a second.
怎么了? 看到什么了?
What? What is it?
某种实验室
Some sort of laboratory.
我们已经碰到很多了
这个城市里到处都是
We've come across dozens of those.
The city's full of them.
这个有什么不寻常么?
Something unusual about it?
我想我得说... 是的
I'd have to say... yes.
星际之门之亚特兰蒂斯
第一季第15集 在我沉睡之前
Season 1: Episode 15 Before I Sleep
听着, 我们不能就这样整天站在这里看着她
Well, we could stand here looking at her all day.
我们要做的是把她弄出这个箱子
What we've got to do is get her out of this box.
Rodney, 我们不能冒那个险
看看她. 她至少有100岁了
Rodney, we can't take that chance.
Look at her. She's at least 100 years old.
这也就是为什么
我们现在要分秒必争了
Which is why every second counts.
我的意思是, 在我们还在这里争论时
她随时可能倒下死掉
I mean, she could drop dead while we stand here arguing.
她怎么可能死掉? 你说过她已经被冷冻了
How can she drop dead? You said she was frozen.
从技术上说, 她的新陈代谢处于停滞状态
Technically, she's in a state of metabolic stasis.
是的, 老化会在很大程度上得以延缓
不过不是完完全全的停止
Aging slowed considerably,
yes, but not entirely suspended.
你是在说这个女人还活着?
You are saying this woman is still alive?
是的
生命信号系统指示还有生命迹象
Yes.
Life-sign systems indicate viability.
根据我能够得到的原始数据
她在那个地方已经呆了一万年了
According to the initial data I've been able to access,
she's been in that chamber for 10,000 years.
一万年?
10,000 years?
看上去还没有超过9000年
Doesn't look a day over 9,000.
从她现在的样子判断, 她会继续以极慢的速度老去
直到最终走向死亡
She'll continue to age at a very slow rate
until she dies, which, judging by the look of her,
看上去更像是这马上就要发生, 而不是再过一段时间
我坚持我最初的观点
seems more likely to occur sooner rather than
later, bringing me back to my original point.
看看他
Look at her.
她太老了, 我担心她会在复苏的过程中死去
She's so old, I'm afraid the process
of reviving her might actually kill her.
我们不能再让
同一个活生生的古人交谈的机会
We cannot let this chance to talk to a living,
breathing ancient slip through our fingers.
从我们的手中滑过
Again.
那么我们谁知道她还记得些什么?
And who knows what state of mind she'll be in?
更不用提她还可能携带有某种恐怖的传染病了
Not to mention the fact she might carrying
some horrifying contagion.
谁知道她对这个城市了解多少?
And who knows what she knows about our city?
更重要的是
她还有可能知道周围哪里存放有ZPM
More importantly,
does she know about any ZPMs lying around?
啊, 这有可能
Ah, there's a thought.
- 唤醒她
- 但是, 博士
- Revive her.
- But, doctor
- 这是我的命令
- 谢谢
- That's my call.
- Thank you.
我一直认为这个城市被遗弃了
And all the time we thought the city was abandoned.
有没有可能亚特兰蒂斯人在离开这里
前往地球的时候把她留下了?
Is it possible the atlantians left her behind
when they abandoned the city for Earth?
也许是她自己想留下
Maybe she wanted to stay behind.
也许是他们把她给忘了
Maybe they forgot about her.
如果是那样, 当她醒来时
肯定会非常愤怒
In which case, she's going to be
really pissed when she wakes up.
如果她能记起所有事情的话
If she remembers anything at all.
呼吸很浅
Breathing shallow.
脉搏很快
Pulse rapid.
我要用脑电图描记器来检查一下脑部的活动
I'll run an E.E.G. To determine any brain activity.
这是什么?
What is it?
我不知道
I don't know.
星际之门的拨号地址, 一共有五个
Gate addresses, five of them.
M7G 677. 我们到过那个星球
M7G 677. We've been to this planet.
Weir博士...
Dr. Weir...
你好
Hello.
你能听到我的声音么?
Can you hear me?
是的, 我怕的就是这个
Yeah, that's what I was afraid of.
冷冻损伤
Freezer burn.
我想她没有被冻僵
I thought she wasn't frozen.
一万年了, 你还想她能够起来活蹦乱跳?
10,000 years, you expect her to dance a bloody jig?
没错, 不过我想说的是眼睛, Carson.
你看看她的眼睛
Yeah, but it's the eyes, Carson.
You got to look at the eyes.
灯还开着, 不过没人在家
(意指老人双眼无神, 灵魂不再)
The lights are on, but nobody's home.
这不需要专业的医学人士就可以知道...
Doesn't take a medical professional to know that...
当然她能够看到我们...
of course she can see us...
而且还可以听见我们
And hear us.
Hello. 感觉怎样?
Hello. How are you feeling?
奏效了
It worked.
什么?
What was that?
- 她说, "奏效了".
- 什么意思?
- She said, "it worked".
- What does that mean?
我的想是某种东西生效了
I assume something worked.
- 是的, 这可真是一针见血
- 谢谢
- Yes, that's very sharp.
- Thank you.
Hello?
她睡着了
She fell asleep.
当她状态更稳定一些的时候
把她转到医务室去
When she's a bit more stable,
transfer her to the infirmary,
我要对她全程录像
记录下一切
and I want video on her at all times,
recording everything.
如果她说了什么
我们可能不会有机会听到第二遍了
We might not get a second chance
at anything she may say.
让我们希望我们能够听到第一遍, 哈?
Let's hope we get a first, huh?
太大了, 是么?
Too big, huh?
我并没有说它太大
我只是在指出它的尺寸
I'm not saying it's too big.
I'm just pointing out its dimensions.
- 好吧, 它还不是那么大
- 先生们
- Well, it's not that big
- Gentlemen?
我们只是想知道在亚特兰蒂斯
是否还有其他我们尚未发现的被冷冻的人
We were just wondering whether there are
any other frozen bodies out there in Atlantis
that we haven't discovered.
而我刚才正在说在短期内
我们还没有办法知道
And I was just saying there's no way
of knowing in the short term.
这就好像要去搜索曼哈顿的
每栋建筑物中的每个房间
It'd be like searching every room
in every building in Manhattan.
这很要花些时间
It'll take a while.
天才知道,  还有什么无法显示在
探测器上的惊人的东西在那儿等着我们
God knows what other kinds of surprises
are out there, not showing up on the sensors.
啊, 那就是我们想要查明的
Ah, that's what we're here to find out.
Weir 博士?
Dr. Weir?
什么?
Yes?
你最好到医务室来
You'd better come to the infirmary.
我们的病人醒了么?
Is our patient awake?
是的, 而且她说了非常不可思议的事情
Aye, and she's saying the most peculiar things.
马上就到
On our way.
她时昏时醒, 仍然很虚弱
不过这个女人身上有点奇怪的东西
She's drifting in and out, still very weak,
but there's something a wee bit odd about this woman.
她叫我Carson.
She called me Carson.
他知道我的名字
She knows my name.
也许是她无意中听到了你和某人的谈话
Maybe she overheard you talking to someone.
不会
No.
当她醒来时, 只有我一个人在这里
I was alone in here when she woke up.
是不是某种潜意识?
What about subconsciously?
- 我听说过某些昏迷中的病人能够听到...
- 不不, 不仅仅是这个
- I've heard stories of coma patients
being able to hear...
- No, no, it's more than that.
她知道很多事
She knows things.
你感觉怎样?
How are you feeling?
看着你
Look at you.
我原以为我再也见不到你们当中的任何人了
I didn't think I'd see any of you again.
实在是太想你们了...
Missed you all so terribly...
甚至是你, Rodney.
Even you, Rodney.
你看到了?
You see?
对不起
I'm sorry?
我们认识你吗?
Do we know you?
哦, 当然
Oh, yes.
我就是你, Elizabeth.
I'm you, Elizabeth.
- 时间旅行?
- 她正是这么说的
- Time travel?
- That's what she said.
她...
She...
不知怎的通过某种方法回到了过去
当时古人还住在这座城市中
somehow found a way to travel back in time
to when the Ancients inhabited the city.
她是如何...
How did she...
做到的?
do this?
这会是当她再次醒来时
我向她询问的首批问题之一
That will be one of the first questions
I ask her when she wakes up again.
如果她能够再次醒来的话
If she ever wakes up again.
我们不要这么快就排除这种可能性
那就是, 这个女人有可能是, 嗯...
Let's not be too quick to exclude the possibility
that the woman might be, um...
用临床术语怎么说来着?
what is the clinical term?
傻子?
Nuts?
她可能是有老年痴呆, 是的, 不过这不能解释
她为什么知道那么多关于我们大家的事情
She may be senile, yes, but that doesn't explain
how she knows so much about all of us.
那么时间旅行真的是可能的么?
Is time travel even possible?
好吧, 根据爱因斯坦的广义相对论
在物理法则中没有什么可以阻止它的发生
Well, according to Einstein's general theory of relativity,
there's nothing in the laws of physics to prevent it.
不过需要提醒你的是
这是极难实现的
Extremely difficult to achieve, mind you.
你需要一定的技术来操纵黑洞, 用它来建立一个虫洞
(这个虫洞)不仅仅是通过了空间的点, 还通过了时间
You need the technology to manipulate
black holes to create wormholes
not only through points in space, but time.
而不是说通过一部漂亮的DeLorean就可以
(DeLorean是《回到未来》三部曲中
可以穿梭时空的一种车子)
Not to mention a really nice DeLorean.
不要跟我谈到那部电影上去
Don't even get me started on that movie.
我喜欢那部电影
I like that movie.
DNA测试结果
Results of the DNA test.
是吻合的
It's a match.
她就是你
She is you.
我知道你在想什么
I know what you're thinking.
如果她已经在那个休眠室中为我们的到来
已经等了数千年了
If she's been waiting in that stasis chamber
all these millennia for us to arrive,
那为什么系统没有在我们到达这里的时候
试图自动唤醒她？
why didn't the system automatically attempt
to revive her the moment we got here?
答案是: 它确实试过了
Answer: it did.
我已经回头仔细察看了
从我们来到这里之后的数据记录
I've been going over the data from our arrival.
我们首先注意到的一件事就是
One of the first things we noticed
休眠实验室所在的城市区域
有一个突发的能量波动
was a sudden power surge in the section
of the city where the stasis lab was.
系统曾经试图唤醒他
只是我们不知道
It was trying to revive her,
only we didn't know that.
我们所看到的只是更多的能量正在从
一个几近耗尽的ZPM中流出
All we saw was more power draining
from an already nearly depleted ZPM,
因此我们关闭了所有的次要系统
so we shut down all secondary systems.
我差点杀了她...
I almost killed her...
你
you.
觉得这非常不可思议么?
How weird is that?
是的
Very.
非常非常不可思议
Very, very weird.
看着你自己...
Looking at yourself...
将会变成什么样子...
How you will be...
实际上, 今后你的样子和她现在并不相同
Actually, how you will be will be
different than how she is right now.
当她返回过去的同时
也制造了一个分离开的现实
See, the moment she went back in time,
she created a separate reality,
第二个你, 生活在一个... 平行的世界中
a second you, living in a... in a parallel world,
这是基于量子论的其中一个解释
according to one of many
interpretations of quantum theory.
我的意思是, 简单的讲,
这个解释认为宇宙, 实际上
I mean, simply put, this interpretation
states that the universe is, in fact,
在决定所对应的每个可能的结果上
分类成无数个自身的副本
split into an infinite number of copies of itself
in which every possible outcome
所有曾经做过的决定都会在这个
拥有无限多层次的多重宇宙的某个地方存在着
to every decision ever made all exists somewhere
in this infinitely layered multi-universe.
简单的讲
Simply put.
是的, 简而言之
Yeah, in a nutshell.
Elizabeth?
我有很多事情要告诉你
There's so much to tell you.
笔记...
The note...
我做过笔记
I had a note.
是的
Yes.
是的, 是的, 是的, 是的
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
我们找到了你的笔记, 请原谅我的率直
We got your note, and forgive my bluntness,
但是我们真的需要知道
你和古人间发生的所有事
but we really need to know everything about
your encounter with the Ancients,
从你发回过去的时刻说起
beginning at the point where you went back in time.
特别是, 你是如何返回过去的
因为那将对我们非常有用
Specifically, how you went back in time,
because that would be very useful for us
Rodney... 让"我"来说
Rodney... let me talk.
那是一个意外
There was an accident.
我记得...
I remember...
我们通过星际之门来到这里...
We arrived through the Stargate...
灯光自动点亮了...
The lights came on by themselves...
当它们感觉到我们时...
Sensing our presence...
谁干的?
Who's doing that?
城市慢慢的开始苏醒...
The city slowly awoke...
Weir博士, 你得来看看这个
Dr. Weir, you have to see this.
有很多东西我都得去看
There are a lot of things I have to see.
当心点
Just be careful.
这里一定是控制室
This must be the control room.
这, 这很显然是他们的DHD
This, this is obviously their version of a DHD.
噢, 很明显
Oh, obviously.
这个地方可能使能量控制系统
某种类型的计算机接口
This area is probably power control systems,
some sort of a computer interface of some kind.
- 你为什么不研究一下?
- 好的, 看, 这里有问题
- Why don't you find out?
- Well, see, that's the hitch.
我们已经让整个城市的照明系统启动了
空气也开始循环
We've got lights coming on all over the city,
air starting to circulate,
可是这些控制台却没有得到任何能量, 因此...
but no power coming out of these consoles, so...
等等,  退回去一会儿
Wait a minute. Back up a second.
事情并不是这样
That isn't the way it happened.
我们到的时候, 所有设备都正常启动了
Everything came online when we arrived.
照明, 计算机, 能量控制, 所有系统
It was lights, computers,
power control systems, everything.
我可以立即就访问到数据库
I was able to access the database immediately.
我碰到的不是这样
That's not what happened.
第一次不是这样
Not the first time.
你没什么能够帮她的吗?
Isn't there something you can give her?
她正处于一个极端脆弱的状态
She's in an extremely fragile state.
她的血压很低, 心跳非常微弱
Her blood pressure is low, her heart is very weak.
如果我使用刺激性药物, 我担心会导致
危险的心律不齐, 甚至是更糟
If I administer a stimulant, I'm afraid it may
induce a dangerous arrhythmia or worse.
我并不是说用某种强力刺激性的药物
只要足够让她每次的清醒多维持几分钟就可以了
I'm not talking about a strong stimulant, just enough
to keep her alert for a few more minutes at a time.
在她每次昏睡之前
我们很难从她那里听到足够多的陈述
We hardly get a couple of words out
of her before she dozes off.
我需要提醒你的是
一个一万岁的女人是很不寻常的
Which, I might remind you,
is not uncommon for a woman of 10,000.
Carson, 我知道你很不情愿
不过相信我, 她可以挺过去的...
Carson, I understand your reticence,
but trust me when I say I believe she can handle it...
而且我知道这也是她想要的
And I know she'd want it.
好吧
Okay.
没事, Carson.
It's okay, Carson.
我只是跟你一样, 因为这些而有些兴奋
I'm just as freaked out about all this as you are.
我们的病人怎么样了?
How's our patient doing?
血压正在上升, 而且正如你所说的
她已经清醒多了
Pressure's improving, and as you can tell,
she's much more alert.
你能起来到别处去看看么?
Are you up for getting out of here?
看到这个城市
这样浮在海面上
Seeing the city like this,
sitting on the surface of the ocean.
你们无法想象我是多么的如释重负
You can't imagine how relieved I am.
你在说什么?
What are you saying?
在第一次中城市没有浮上来么?
The city didn't rise the first time 'round?
是的
No.
没有
从我们来到这里的那一刻开始
城市就陷入了很大的麻烦之中
The city was in serious trouble
from the very moment we arrived.
我们正在尝试使用临时的电池电力
来接通这些控制台
We're trying to interface these consoles
with temporary battery power,
看看我们能否访问城市的主能源系统
然后让这里运作起来
see if we can access the city's main power systems
and get this place up and running.
Weir博士,  Sumner上校
Dr. Weir, colonel Sumner.
能请你下来到我这里看看么?
我们在你下面三层
Can you come down here and meet me, please?
We're three levels down from you.
就来
Right away.
我们能够做些什么?
How we doing over there?
目前什么都不行
Nothing yet.
好吧, 那就让我们来看看我们能做的
Well, let's see what we can do, then.
我们只能保护这个地方的一小片区域
We've only been able to secure a fraction of the place.
它太大了
It's huge.
这么说这真的可能是哪个失去的城市, 亚特兰蒂斯了
So it might really be the lost city of Atlantis.
我想很有可能
I'd say that's a good bet.
噢, 上帝
Oh, my god.
我们在水下
We're underwater.
我想说我们是在海面几百英尺以下
I'd say we're under several hundred feet of ocean.
这会是一个麻烦
This could be a problem.
哦, 不
Oh, no.
Weir博士, 我需要你马上到控制室来
Dr. Weir, I need to see you
in the control room immediately.
这个城市有一个防护罩, 某种能量力场
正是它把海水挡在外面
The city has a shield, some sort of
a energy force field holding the water back.
就是说, 它曾经有一个防护罩
That is, it had a shield.
能量系统已经接近输出的最大限度了
The power systems are nearing maximum entropy.
我们的到来大大加快的它们的损耗
Our arrival hastened their depletion, big time.
我的意思是,  你可以看到, 防护罩正在快速的崩溃
I mean, you can see, the shield is collapsing rapidly.
城市的一些部分已经被洪水淹没
Several sections of the city are already flooded.
我们可以使用自己的发电机么?
Can we use our own power generators?
我怀疑我们的naquadah发电机无法提供
足够的能量来维持防护罩
I doubt our naquadah generators can supply
enough power to sustain the shield,
而且我们也几乎没有时间来试了
and we probably don't have time to try.
我说的是快速的崩溃, 我指的是快速
When I say rapidly collapsing, I mean rapidly.
Sumner少校, 我要你命令你的安全卫队
停止搜索这个城市
Colonel Sumner, I need youto order
all your security teams to stop searching the city
立即撤退到星际之门所在的房间
and fall back to the gateroom immediately.
Sumner, 你听到了么?
Sumner, do you copy?
Weir博士, 我是Sumner...
Dr. Weir, this is Sumner...
Sumner上校淹死了?
Colonel Sumner drowned?
而且他不是唯一的牺牲者
And he wasn't the only one to perish.
我们应该通过星际之门将人们疏散出去
We should start evacuating people through the Stargate.
做不到
We can't.
现在系统中剩余的能量已经被转到防护罩上去了
为了抵挡海水
Whatever power's left in the system has been diverted
to sustaining the shield holding the ocean back.
为什么会发生在现在?
Do we know why this is happening now?
防护罩本可以继续抵挡海水100年的
The shield might've held the water back
for another 100 years,
但是我们到来之后
能量的消耗急剧的提高了
but power consumption spiked when we arrived.
它的发生是由于我们的到来?
This is happening because we arrived?
是的
Yes.
那后备能量呢?
What about auxiliary power?
我会尝试使用我们自己的一个发电机
来接通星际之门
I'll try to interface the gate
with one of our generators.
希望时间足够
Hopefully there's enough time.
Grodin, 查询一下星际之门控制系统
看看我们能不能在数据库中找到一些星际之门的拨号地址
Grodin, access the Stargate control systems, see if
you can locate any gate addresses in the database.
我们可能没有足够的能量返回地球
不过也许我们有足够的能量到达飞马座的其它什么地方
Won't be nearly enough power to gate back to Earth, but
maybe we'll have enough to gate elsewhere in pegasus.
队伍中有人发现了一个航空港
里面全部是他们称之为船的东西
Some of our team discovered a bay full
of what they're calling ships.
就像是太空船?
As in space ships?
我们应该去看看
We should check them out.
- 你认为你能够驾驶么
- 我差不多可以飞任何东西
- You think you could figure out
- I could fly just about anything.
好的, 去吧
Good. Go
- 我将从这个开始, 你从那些
- 我们在找什么?
- I'll start with this. You start with one of those.
- What am i looking for?
看看它们能够装多少人
也许我们可以飞离这里
See how many people they can fit.
Maybe we can fly out of here.
城市的两片平台已经完全被水淹没了
第三块也快崩溃了!
Two piers of the city are almost entirely flooded,
a third about to collapse as well!
Weir博士, 这些飞船看起来对我们非常有用
Dr. Weir, these ships look like a good fallback.
每艘都可以装不少人
They can hold several people each.
学习如何驾驶它们是另外一个问题
Learning how to fly them's going to be another matter.
我看看我能够在城市的示意图上找到一条出路
I'll see if I can pull up a schematic, find a way out.
这艘船跟其它的不太一样
This ship seems different than the others.
怎么不同?
Different how?
它有一个与众不同的控制台
It's a different control console.
我已经用无线电通知了Zelenka.
他正在赶来检查的路上
I've radioed Zelenka.
He's on his way over to check it out.
- 好的, 我也过来看看
- 哦, 不
- Good, I'm on my way, too.
- Oh, no.
怎么了?
What's wrong?
这个城市正在进入最后的自我保护模式
The city's going into a last-gasp self-protect mode.
城市中的防水墙正在迅速的关闭当中
Airtight bulkheads are slamming shut all over the city.
我们已经有人被困住了
We've got people trapped.
- 那不会保护他们么?
- 太少了, 太迟了
- Wouldn't that protect them?
- It's too little, too late.
大部分的房间已经被破坏了
持续上升的海水已经困住了我们很多人
Most of the rooms are already breached.
We've got people trapped with water rising.
该死
Damn.
我试试取消系统的自我控制
I'll try to override the system,
打开那些门, 不过这会严重影响
向星际之门输入能量
open the doors, but that's seriously
hampering efforts to rig power to the Stargate.
如果那些飞船是我们离开这里的唯一方法
If these ships turn out to be our only way out of here,
我可不想等得太久以至于无法到达航空港
I don't want you waiting too long to get up to the bay.
Rodney...
yes, yes, yes, 我听到了
yes, yes, yes, I heard.
去吧
Go.
怎么样了?
How are we doing?
这艘飞船跟其它船不一样
This ship is different than the others.
是的, 这我知道
为什么? 它是用来做什么的?
Yeah, we know that. Why? What's it do?
我不知道 我需要更多时间
I do not know. I will need more time.
我们没有时间了
We don't have time.
它是密封的, 我想
It's airtight, I assume.
它是太空船, 应该是
It's a space ship. It'd better be.
Sheppard少校, 我在航空港的屋顶找到了一个舱门
我看看能不能打开它
Major Sheppard, I've located a roof hatch
in the gate ship bay.  I'll try to get it open.
那是什么?
What was that?
控制室外的密封门已经全部都关闭了
我们被锁在里面了
Bulkhead doors leading out of the control room
have all slammed shut. We're locked in.
你能把它打开么?
Can you get it open?
我正在努力!
I'm trying!
别管那个了. gate room已经进水了
Forget it. The gate room's flooding.
把门打开到这里来, 我们在这里等你们
Get them open and get up here.
We're waiting for you.
Elizabeth, 我们准备继续尝试收回屋顶
只要它打开了, 我们就走
Elizabeth, we're going to keep trying to
retract the roof. As soon as it opens, you go.
Rodney...
没有时间来争论了! 灾难就在眼前
Look, there's no time to argue!
Catastrophic failure is imminent.
把你们自己管好, 走吧
Just lock yourself in and go.
尽管你已经尽力了
你还是什么也做不了, Rodney.
Despite your efforts,
there was nothing you could do, Rodney.
不久以后, 控制室就被水淹没了
Within seconds, the control room was flooded.
我死了?
I died?
你没有放弃努力, 一直到最后
You never gave up trying, right until the end.
好吧...
Well...
作为男人我很想知道, 当面临如此可怕的情况时
我会如何选择
A man wonders how he would choose to go out,
given such dire circumstances.
现在我知道了
Now I know.
试图拯救其他人的生命
Trying to save the lives of others.
不过最终还是失败了
But ultimately failing.
- 我敢肯定如果我拥有的时间可以再多几秒, 我就可以..
- 等等
- I'm sure if I had a few more seconds, I could...
- Wait a second.
为什么自动保障机制没有把城市浮上水面?
Why didn't the failsafe mechanism engage
and raise the city to the surface?
因为第一次没有自动保障机制
Because there was no failsafe the first time.
Atlantis继续留在海底
Atlantis remained on the ocean floor.
防护罩完全崩溃
The shield completely collapsed.
海水冲了进来
流进城市中的每个房间
Water came crashing in,
flooding every room in the city.
你们两个在试图帮助其他人
登上飞船的时候淹死了
You both drowned while attempting
to get our people into ships,
而我们, 同 Zelenka一起,
发现我们自己也被困住了
and we, along with Dr. Zelenka,
we found ourselves trapped.
我们需要离开这里!
We need to get out of here!
McKay把舱门打开了么?
Did McKay get the hatch open?
我不知道
I do not know.
少校, 我们有六个人挤在了一艘船里
我们应该怎么做?
Major, there's six of us stuck in
one of the ships! What do we do?
你干了什么?
What did you do?
我不知道
我想我刚把它打开了
I don't know.
I think I just turned it on.
待命, 中士
Stand by, sergeant.
我没怎么看过说明手册
不过我好像可以正确的操作它
I'm not much for instruction manuals,
but I could use one right about now.
哦, 我的天哪
Oh, my god.
这是在宇宙空间中
发生什么了?
It's space.
What happened?
现在你想做什么?
Now what did you do?
我不知道, 我只是...
I don't know. I just...
那是什么?
What was that?
我们受到了攻击
We were under attack.
我们不知道我们在哪里
也不知道谁在朝我们射击
We didn't know where we were
or who was shooting at us.
然后那时John...
And that's when John...
- Carson!
- 我是Beckett.
- This is Beckett.
我需要医疗帮助
在会议室, 快
I need medical assistance
in the conference room asap.
她怎样了?
How's she doing?
稳定下来了, 不过仍然非常虚弱
并且正在变得更加虚弱
Stabilized, but still very weak,
and getting weaker.
濒临死亡的你
正注视着你自己的脸
Your own mortality,
staring you right in the face.
我无法想象你此时的感受
I can't imagine how you must be feeling.
当她看着我的时候, 就好像她在感知我的心灵
同时我也在感知她的心灵
When she looks at me, it's as if she's
sensing my thoughts, and I'm sensing hers.
这很让人不安
It's very unsettling.
在你这么想的时候
我觉得没有什么比这更不可思议的了
Just when you thought this
place couldn't get any weirder.
好吧, 很明显
Well, it's obvious.
他们逃跑时所乘坐的飞船一定是某种时间机器
The puddle jumper they escaped in must've
been some sort of a time machine.
在它内部, 一定装配有某种特殊的组件
It had to have an additional
component built into it.
Flux capacitor
(电影《回到未来》里时间机器的核心部件)
Flux capacitor.
是的, 问题是
时间机器现在在哪里?
Yeah, question is,
where is the time machine now?
我们为什么不问问她?
Why don't we ask her?
发生什么了?
What happened?
你能告诉我们么?
Can you tell us?
你们逃离时所乘坐的飞船
它现在在哪?
The ship that you escaped in,
where is it now?
没有了
It's gone.
是谁在向我们射击?
Who is shooting at us?
现在更好的问题是
我们应该如何还击?
Better question is,
how do we shoot back?
这是我做的么?
Did I do that?
抓好了!
Hang on!
接下来我所知道的就是...
The next thing I knew...
我在这里醒来
I woke up here.
什么, 你说现在?
What, you mean now?
不是
No.
那时
Then.
你醒了
You're awake.
他的名字叫Janus.
His name was Janus.
他治好了我的伤
并向我解释发生了什么
He healed my wounds and
explained to me what had happened.
你们的飞船被击落了
Your ship was shot down.
我们在海底找到了它
We retrieved it from the ocean floor.
Sheppard少校, Zelenka博士呢?
Major Sheppard, Dr. Zelenka?
他们没有生还
No one survived.
哈! 啊, 你也品尝一下终极失败的痛苦吧
Ha! Ah, the bitter
taste of ultimate failure.
如果你能够找到
修好那个该死的防护罩的方法的话
Well, if you had just figured out
how to fix the damn shield
从一开始, 我们当中就不会有人会死了
in the first place,
none of us would've died.
我已经尽我所能了, 包括试图拯救你们那英勇的努力...
抱歉
I did everything I could, including valiantly
attempting to save your... sorry
先生们... 注意点
Gentlemens... focus.
请继续
Please continue.
不必说, 我当时非常困惑
Needless to say, I was very confused.
他对我解释说
我逃离时所乘坐的飞船是...
He explained to me that
the ship we had escaped in was...
一个时间机器
a time machine.
而他就是这个机器的建造者
He was the one who built it.
在我感觉好点之后
他把我带到亚特兰蒂斯人的议会面前
After I was feeling better,
he brought me before the atlantian council.
我们欢迎你来到亚特兰蒂斯城
We welcome you to the city of Atlantis.
谢谢
Thank you.
很不幸, 你的到来正好赶上了这里的战争
Unfortunately, your arrival has
come at a time of great conflict.
我们已经被围困了多年
而且作为一个保护措施, 我们把城市沉入了海底
We've been under siege for many years and have
submerged our city as a measure of protection.
是的, 这非同寻常
Yes, it's extraordinary.
这就是我们通过星际之门来到这里时所发现的
It's how we found the city when
we came through the Stargate.
从地球?
From Earth?
是的
Yes.
距今一万年后
10,000 years from now.
这很值得关注, 我们的所采取的行为
成功的保护了城市这么多年
It should be noted that our actions have
succeeded in protecting the city for so many years.
我们非常希望Weir博士的到来
没有改变这个的可能性
Let us hope Dr. Weir's arrival
has not altered this eventuality.
不过因为跟幽灵的直接接触
她可能已经影响了
By directly encountering the Wraith,
she may have already set in motion
一系列的事件
这将会使我们的未来与她离开的那个未来很不相同
a chain of events that could lead to a
future far different from the one she left.
对不起, 幽灵是什么?
I'm sorry, what are the Wraith?
他们告诉我那种被称为幽灵的生物
They told me of beings called Wraith,
邪恶的, 可怕的敌人
他们的力量和科技无人能敌
a vicious, formidable enemy whose
power and technology rivaled their own.
是的, 事实上, 我们已经...
Yes, actually, we've already...
亚特兰蒂斯人派出了一个
在他们最强大的舰队保护下的代表团
The atlantians sent a delegation protected
by their most powerful warships
为了达成停战协议这个微弱的希望...
in the faint hope of negotiating a truce...
一对一的话, 亚特兰蒂斯人的飞船更强大
不过幽灵实在是太多了
one on one, atlantian ships were
more powerful, but the Wraith were so many.
在那场大战之后...
After that great battle...
亚特兰蒂斯人的失败只是时间问题了
it was only a matter of time.
我们正在等待最后一艘
从其他星球返回的运输船
We're awaiting the last of
our off-world transport ships
然后我们就会开始通过星际之门进行撤退
before beginning our evacuation
through the Stargate.
你们要去哪里?
Where will you go?
我们会返回地球
We're returning to Earth.
欢迎你加入我们
You are welcome to join us.
谢谢
Thank you.
这个举动非常友好, 不过...
That's very kind, but...
我想你应该了解
我渴望回到未来, 我到我的人民中去
I'm sure you must understand my desire
to return to the future, to my people.
我希望我能够再次使用时间机器
I was hoping I would be able
to use the time machine again,
设置它到达的时间
正好为我们刚刚穿过星际之门那一刻
and program it to arrive at the precise
moment we came through the Stargate,
并且, 如果可能的话, 希望能让我带走一个ZPM
那将会极大的帮助我们.
and if it was possible, and you had a ZPM I could
take back with me, that would help us considerably.
要知道, 这个城市的能源系统
到那时实际上已经快耗尽了...
See, the power systems of the
city were virtually depleted when...
不行 对时间的干涉已经够多的了
No. Enough of this tampering with time.
因果关系不应该被如此轻率的对待
Causality is not to be treated so lightly.
没有人在轻率的对待它
No one's treating it lightly.
你就在, 正是由于你坚持进行的那些实验
You are, with your insistence
on continuing these experiments
无视议会的指责
despite the condemnation of this council.
我们命令你停止这些活动
然而我们现在却坐在这里
We ordered you to cease these
activities, and yet here we sit,
面对着来自未来的一个访客
face to face with a visitor from the future
而她正是乘坐着那个你承诺不再
建造的机器到来的
who arrived here in the very machine
you agreed not to construct.
我们正准备从这个城市撤离
只是希望它能够安全的屹力很多年
We are about to evacuate this city in
the hope that it will lie safe for many years,
直到某一天, 我们的种族将会回来...
and then one day, our kind will return...
他们做到了
and they have.
正是由于我的实验
我们现在才有机会...
It is because of my experiments
that we now have the opportunity...
够了! 我们没有时间争论这个了
Enough! We have no time for this.
我现在正式命令摧毁这个时间旅行装置
I am hereby ordering the
destruction of this time-travel device
以及所有和它的设计有关的材料
and all the materials
connected with its design.
欢迎你和我的人民一起返回地球
You are welcome to
return to Earth with our people.
你不能回到你的人民中去
You shall not be returning to yours.
检查结果的最后一组数据
更明显的确定了我的判断
The last set of test results
only confirm the obvious.
她的骨骼、肌肉、循环系统和神经系统
全部都被岁月严重侵蚀了
Her skeletal, muscular, circulatory, and
neuroendocrine systems have all been decimated by age.
我已经观测到了肾衰竭、肝衰竭
以及她最近的虚脱对他身体所造成的损伤
I'm seeing renal failure, liver failure,
and evidence of a stroke from her recent collapse.
她还有多长时间?
How long does she have?
我怀疑她活不过今晚了
I doubt she'll live out the night.
请...
Please...
我不知道我还剩多少时间
来向你们讲述这个
我已经等待了这么久想要告诉你们的故事
I don't know how much time I have left
to tell the story I've waited so long to tell.
议会...
The council...
他们非常不安...
they were very upset...
是的
yes.
你说了他们决定毁掉那个时间机器
You said they decided
to destroy the time machine.
我试图说服他们
I tried to talk them out of it.
我不能放弃希望
I couldn't give up hope.
感谢上天, 我有一个支持者
Thankfully, I had an ally.
你需要和Moros谈谈
You need to talk to Moros.
Weir博士被带到这里并不是她的错
Dr. Weir was brought here
through no fault of her own.
她不应该为此而受到惩罚
She shouldn't be punished for it.
她可以跟我们回到地球
并自由的跟我们生活在一起
She's free to come with us back
to Earth and live among our kind
她需要回到她的时代
而不是留在我们当中
she needs to return to
her time, not remain in ours.
这是不可能的
That's not possible.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
等一下
Wait.
我想你并不了解我们已经付出了多少
I don't think you understand
how far we've come
以及我的人民做出了多大的牺牲
只是希望能够见到你们
or how much my people have
sacrificed in the hopes of meeting you.
我们称你们为古人
We call you the Ancients.
星际之门的建造者
The gate builders.
我们穿越了数个星系
只是希望能够找到一个伟大的民族
We've crossed galaxies in
the hopes of finding a great people.
求你了, 难道你们就没有其它的方法可以帮助我了么?
Please, is there no other way you can help?
我们可以在撤离之后永久封闭星际之门
We could block the Stargate
permanently after the evacuation.
这样, 在将来, 你们的队伍
就不可能会来到这里
That way, in the future, your
team will be unable to come here.
如果他们无法到来
这个城市就永远都不会被发现
If they can't come,
the city may never be found.
但是她的探险队中的那些人的生命就会得救
But the lives of her
expedition would be saved.
感谢你的慷慨提议
不过我们是探险者, 正如你们一样
Thank you for your generous offer,
but we are explorers, just like you.
这不奇怪 因为他们是我们这个人种的第二次进化
Which should come as no surprise, since
they are the second evolution of our kind.
你还没有理解么?
Don't you understand?
这个城市将会生存一万年
This city will survive 10,000 years.
议会的决定是无法修改的
The council's decision is final.
当然, Janus拒绝承认失败
Of course, Janus refused to concede defeat.
别人越是告诉他不要这么做
他就越是要这么做
The more someone told him not to
do something, the more he had to do it.
所以他背着议会另外准备了一份方案
So he came up with an
alternate plan behind the council's back.
我所能做的就是尽量跟上他
It was all I could do
to try to keep pace with him.
我可以问一下你现在正在做什么吗?
May I ask what it is you're doing?
计算必要的能量需求
Calculating the necessary power needed.
需要用来...
Needed for...
你说过, 在你们到达之后不久
防护罩就崩溃了
You said the shield collapsed
shortly after your arrival.
我必须找到一个尽量延长能量供给的方法
I have to find a way to
extend the supply of power.
你们把它们称作什么?
What is it you called them?
ZPM
ZPM.
零点模块
(Zero Point Module)
Zero point module.
是的...
Yes...
他们本被设计用来并行工作
所有三个同时为城市提供能量
They're designed to operate in parallel, all
three providing power to the city simultaneously.
然而  如果依次使用的话
就有可能保存必要的能量, 以备必要时使用
However, used in sequence, it may be possible to
sustain the necessary power for the needed time.
我简直无法相信我的眼睛
I couldn't believe my eyes.
三个ZPM, 正在我的面前
Three ZPMs, right in front of me.
不过, 还是有一个小问题
There is one small problem, however.
必须有人留在城市里
让能量从一个设备转移到另外一个
Someone will need to remain behind in the city to
transfer the power from one device to the other,
依次替换它们
to rotate them sequentially.
在这数千年间?
Over thousands of years?
这是可能的
It is possible.
Janus, 请向控制中心报告
Janus, please report to central control.
他们的运输船归航了
Their transport ship was inbound.
它遭受到了强大火力的攻击
It was taking heavy fire.
防御罩被摧毁了! 我们正在还击, 不过我们无法前进!
敌船的数目实在是太多了
Cloaking shields damaged! We're returning fire, but
we cannot access! There's too many enemy ships.
而且还有更多正在赶来
And there are more coming.
启用辅助动力  尽量摆脱他们
Engage auxiliary power.
Try to outrun them.
那艘运输船上有超过300人
There are over 300 people on that transport.
开始撤离
Begin evacuation.
我们必须离开, 现在
We must leave, now.
该死, 我又睡着了
Damn, fell asleep again.
你不是唯一睡着的
Well, you're not the only one.
你现在觉得痛苦么?
Are you in any pain?
就算是, 你觉得我们会承认么?
Would we admit it if we were?
我希望我们能为你再做些什么
I wish there was more
we could do for you.
噢, 看你
Oh, look at you.
总是那么烦恼
Always worrying.
你给自己施加的压力太大了
You put too much pressure on yourself.
还记得么...
Remember...
那次悲惨的波罗的海谈判么?
that miserable baltic negotiation?
simon在那之后跟我们说了些什么?
What simon told us afterwards?
呼吸?
Breathe?
在其它事物之中
Among other things.
享受当前的时光
Enjoy the moment.
现在所拥有的, 阳光, 微风...
What's here right now,
the sun, the breeze...
我们的生日
our birthday.
Sheppard没法守住这个秘密, 对么?
Sheppard couldn't keep it to himself, huh?
我只是想说, 不要再对自己那么刻薄了
I'm just saying stop being
so damn hard on yourself.
生命短暂
Life is quick.
对你而言不是
Not for you.
这是我的选择, Elizabeth.
It was my choice, Elizabeth.
我当时无法预知它的后果...
I didn't second-guess it then...
我现在也无怨无悔
and I don't regret it now.
Weir博士在哪里?
Where is Dr. Weir?
她已经通过星际之门了
She's gone through the gate.
她是第一批撤离的
She was among the first to evacuate.
很好
Good.
Janus为我准备了休眠室
Janus prepared the stasis chamber for me.
他说那就像是一个深沉的 无梦的睡眠
Said it would be like a deep, dreamless sleep.
我正在输入指令
让系统唤醒你两次
I'm inputting commands for
the system to revive you twice,
其中的间隔大约是三千三百年
这样你就可以轮换ZPM
at intervals of approximately 3.3 thousand
years so that you can rotate the ZPMs.
接下来我会给你重新激活休眠程序的操作说明
I'll give you instructions on how to
reactivate the stasis process afterwards.
我还输入了一些必须的指令
当传感器探测到你的探险队到达之时
I'm also entering the necessary commands to
commence final revival the moment sensors
就开始最终的唤醒程序
indicate the presence of your expedition team.
我觉得我有必要告诉你
存在一种可能性
Look, I feel that I must tell
you that there is a possibility,
尽管可以持续很久
不过它还是可能不会成功
remote as it is,
that this might not succeed.
我知道
I know.
无法预测在那么长的时间内将会发生什么
It's impossible to predict what'll
happen over such a long period of time.
我坚信 你会活下来的
I'm convinced that you will survive.
不过尽管你不能成功的可能性非常小
But in the highly unlikely
eventuality that you don't,
我还是编织了一个自动保护机制
来保护这个城市
I've programmed a failsafe
mechanism to protect the city.
自动保护?
A failsafe?
是的, 如果能量输出低到了一个危险的水平
Yes, if the power drains to a critical level,
将城市保持在洋底的机制将会释放
城市将会上浮到海面
the mechanism holding the city on the ocean floor
will release, and it will rise to the surface.
真的?
Really?
然后他们就离开了, 他们所有人
通过星际之门回到了地球
and then they left, all of them,
returning to Earth through the Stargate.
这些是什么?
What's all that?
我的研究
My research.
你想再建造一艘时间船?
You're going to build another time ship?
我不知道是否能成功
委员会将会监视我的一举一动
I doubt I'll succeed, seeing that the
council will be watching my every move.
你相信你会找到方法的
I'm sure you'll find a way.
我已经屏蔽了除了地球以外
所有到这个星际之门的拨号地址
I've blocked all addresses
to the gate except Earth.
你会是安全的
You will be safe.
谢谢你
Thank you.
谢谢你, 是你给了我希望
亚特兰蒂斯仍然会生存
Thank you, for giving me
the hope that Atlantis will survive
再过一万年
在你再次发现它之后
another 10,000 years
after you discover it again.
我准备好了
I'm ready.
然后就只剩下我一个人了
And then I was alone.
我把城市设为休眠状态...
I set the city to slumber...
然后开始我那漫长的回家之旅
and began my long journey home.
它奏效了, 休眠, 自动保护
It worked, the stasis, the failsafe.
你献出了你的整个一生
You gave up your entire life.
不, 因为我们是同一个人
No, because we are the same person.
我生命中最美好的部分才刚刚开始
The best part of my life is just beginning.
我就要去探索新的星系
I'm exploring a new galaxy.
我眼前还有很长的岁月
I have years ahead of me still.
相信你自己, Elizabeth.
Trust yourself, Elizabeth.
所有的事情...
All that matters...
就是现在
is right now.
那个笔记, 我写下它, 是怕万一我无法活下来
The note, I wrote it in case I didn't survive.
Rodney看明白了么?
Has Rodney figured it out yet?
五个星际之门的地址
Five gate addresses.
他们是前哨战...
Outposts...
每处都有一个零点模块
each one with a zero point module.
Janus 告诉我的
Janus told me.
她留下的那个笔记,  是已知的拥有ZPM的行星
The note she left, it's coordinates
of planets to have known ZPMs.
它们应该还在那
They could still be there.
M7G 677在这上面
M7G 677's on here.
这太令人惊奇了
Elizabeth, 我们曾经到过...
This is amazing.
Elizabeth, we've got...
我们正准备开始我们的任务简报, 所以...
We're about to start our mission briefing, so...
我就过来
I'll be right there.
事实上, John
Actually, John?
让我独自呆几分钟, 好么?
Give me a minute, will you?
当然可以
Sure.